PORTFOLIO-PROJECT AND PRODUCT CREATED IN MY CAREER

'Click Here' To View

PROFILE

Innovative and creative EEE Engineer with 5+ years of experience in designing and developing electronic systems.

I have developed & executed about 250+ projects and 3+ products in my career.

Extremely motivated to constantly develop my skills and grow professionally. I am confident in my ability to come up with interesting Innovative ideas.

CONTACT



Puducherry



ajithvenkatason10@gmail.com



8220647389



AJITH KUMAR V

Product Development Engineer, Electronic Systems

Work Experience

Product Development Engineer

CHEMIN C&I Pvt Ltd - Puducherry

Aug 2022 -Sep 2023

My role is to design and develop the product, covering aspects from ideation, prototyping, design, and commercialization. Below are the domains I have worked on during product development.

- Project Management: Proficiently managed project lifecycles, from inception to completion, including team management, work assignment, project flow planning, roadmap creation, version control, and meticulous data structure planning. Successfully selected development platforms, planned and prioritized features, validated UI/UX designs and conducted thorough app/website testing.
- Technical Expertise/Electronics Development: Expertise in chip selection, embedded C programming, component selection, and sourcing. Oversaw prototyping, PCB designing, and testing. Played a pivotal role in choosing and sourcing enclosures, designing packaging, and branding products.
- Production Planning: Managed all aspects of production, including component selection, sourcing, and quality assurance, ensuring timely delivery of high-quality products.
- **Market Analysis:** Conducted in-depth market studies and surveys, formulated effective market strategies, and contributed to sales planning.
- Content Creation: Spearheaded content creation, including videos, photos, posters, and stickers, from planning and shooting to editing, enhancing brand visibility and engagement.
- Documentation and Innovation: Proficient in creating flowcharts, comprehensive documentation, and product innovation and ideation. Ensured quality assurance, meticulously validating designs and manufacturing processes.
- **Training:** Delivered theoretical and practical classes during internships, nurturing the skills and knowledge of emerging professionals.
- Quotation Preparation: Skillfully prepared quotations for IOT/Electronics simulation SKID and Kit, guaranteeing precise pricing and comprehensive offerings.

Product Worked: IOT Based Home Automation Device

Description: Home appliances can be controlled through an App or Website.

Brand Name: Chemin IntelliGB Model Name: Control Node

Design and Development Engineer

Schopig Automation I Puducherry

Jul 2018 - Aug 2022

My role is to design and develop the product, covering aspects from ideation, prototyping and designing. Below are the domains I have worked on during product development.

- Team Management: Proficiently led and managed a maintenance team, overseeing responsibilities from inception to completion. Expertly managed team assignments, devised machine maintenance flow plans and organized periodic maintenance schedules. Additionally, conducted comprehensive training for the maintenance team.
- Technical Expertise/Electronics Development: Demonstrated expertise in chip selection, embedded C programming and meticulous component selection. Oversaw prototyping, PCB design, and comprehensive testing. Key involvement in the selection, sourcing and design of machine enclosures, strands and cup dispensers.
- **Production Planning:** Managed the entire production cycle, ensuring meticulous component selection, sourcing and rigorous quality assurance for the timely delivery of high-quality products.
- **Innovation:** Instrumental in product innovation and ideation, consistently enhancing the overall system based on customer feedback and addressing system lag or issues.

AJITH KUMAR V

Product Development Engineer, Electronic Systems



- Testing: Conducted diverse tests to ensure the product's seamless operation 24/7 without any issues, emphasizing reliability and performance.
- Training: Facilitated both theoretical and practical internship classes, imparting
 essential skills and knowledge to shape the expertise of upcoming professionals.

Product Worked: UPI payments acceptable Fully automatic Beverage vending machine

Description: The fully automated vending machine allows seamless UPI payments, ensuring quick and convenient transactions for beverages on the go.

Brand Name: Bestea

Model Name: Manual, fully automatic (2,3 and 4 Lane) and Elite fully automatic

Product Worked: Juz wallet

Description: Juz enables payments via Juz wallet, utilizing an NFC card or mobile phone for seamless and efficient transactions.

Brand Name: Bestea

Model Name: Juz Scan and Juz Tap



Project Development Engineering Techtilt Info Solution I Puducherry

Jun 2017 - Jul 2018

- My role is to develop a hardware-embedded project in the electrical and electronics domain based on the student and industry requirements. I worked on most of the Digital/Analog sensors and communications.
- On student projects, I developed innovative projects like E-cycle, IOT-based irrigation systems etc.
- On the industries side, I develop product solutions for their technical problems. I
 worked with more than three companies.
- I conducted various weekly workshops and courses in colleges/institutes regarding embedded C programming/Hardware integration.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

PCB Design Arduino

Industrial Automation Home Automation

Embedded C Product Development

Reverse Engineering Custom PC Build

R & D Altium

Education

Bachelor of Technology (B.Tech,EEE)

Rajivgandhi college of engineering - Puducherry

Academic Project-Smart Street lighting using arduino

Diploma in EEE (DEEE)

Krishnasawamy politechnic college - Cuddalore

Academic Project-PLC Based jogging and inching

SLCC

2010 - 2011

Seventh day her sec school - Puducherry

69%

HOBBIES

Custom Sound System Tech News

Product Development Listening Music

Innovation Projects

Accomplishment

- · Industrial automation from certification Omron e-learning
- Won 1st prize in the renewable energy club held in my college
- I conducted practical workshops and trained many students
- I taught many batches for the IIT competition
- · I presented various guest lectures.